BFSI Delivery Head - Head of Digital & Data - Digital Transformation Lead

With an international background in business and technology, I have delivered BFSI solutions and products to the USA, UK, France, and Middle East markets for more than 25 years. I pride myself for focusing on delivering strategic outcomes for the clients, using the latest technologies, data solutions, AI/ML, cloud, automation, agile, and DevOps processes. I have been a client partner for Tier I banks like RBS, UBS, HSBC, Fidelity, P66.

I have managed large multi country implementations, secured new business across regions, and delivered customer facing BFSI solutions by creating successful digital and data teams, ODCs, and building businesses leveraging technology solutions.

I have brought about digital and data transformation for global teams, by changing technology, processes, and culture, to enable delivery of client value more frequently and efficiently, saving money in the process.

Before joining Sopra Banking to be the Domain head and Digital-Data Transformation head, I was a Senior Director playing the role of the Delivery Head, Digital Transformation Lead, and Data Lead for a large global technology services organization.

My technical foundation as a developer-architect in implementing solutions, and my subsequent leadership, business and digital transformation skills are the basis of my continued success in project delivery. I hold multiple agile and technical certifications and am doing my Masters in Data Science. I am a tech guy at heart and ensuring that teams deliver customer value quickly and continuously transform and improve is what energizes me.

Skills

Technology And Business Leadership - Digital Leadership - Transformation Leadership - Building Products, Solutions, Applications - Consulting - Strategic Delivery Management - Setting Up and Growing Teams - Senior Leadership Management - Client Management - IT Roadmap - Agile - DevOps - AI, ML, Data Science - Data Engineering - Sales - P&L Management

BFSI - Investment Banking - Capital Markets - Retail Banking - Investment Management - Equity - Equity Derivatives - Fixed Income - Market Risk - Regulatory Reporting - Lending - Mortgages - 401K

Highlights / Accomplishments

- Led multiple digital transformation and data transformation journeys for Tier I banks, by leveraging cloud, data, cutting edge technologies, DevOps and agile ways of working, resulting in 20M+USD savings for banks.
- Built Data Analytics & Insight Solutions to optimize pipelines for Tier I commodity client.
- Built Data lake for market risk data for Tier I Investment Bank using Big Data technologies.
- Built a Tier I bank ODC to 500+ size with 40+ Million USD annual revenue across all asset classes. Led the show from contract negotiation to team hiring and building to high quality delivery.
- Setup a Tier I Investment management ODC of 150+ people.
- Renowned in the company as an expert on Digital Transformation, Data Transformation, Agile and DevOps.

Certifications

- Agile Certifications: Certified Scrum Professional (CSP), Certified Scrum Master (CSM), Certified SAFe Agelist.
- <u>Technical Certifications</u>: Certified Google Cloud Data Engineer, Certified Google Cloud Architect, MongoDB University Certified Developer.
- Misc. Certifications: Dale Carnegie certified for public speaking, Duarte Certified for presentation skills

Articles and Publications

- Financial Sentiment Analysis using FinBert https://bit.ly/3GTW8ce
- Data Visualization: Why 3D charts are a terrible idea https://bit.ly/3sK6hTZ

Experience

Sopra Banking Software, India

Domain Head

Digital & Data Transformation Head (Saving, Mortgage & Regulatory Reporting Products) | 2020-Present

- Spearheading the digital transformation and delivering Mortgage & Saving products with high speed, quality, and value.
- Leading digital & data transformation of the Regulatory Reporting product using data engineering, AWS, MongoDB, Microservices, Angular, and Java technologies.
- Painted the vision and laid out the strategy of continuous and frequent delivery with high automation for the team. Bought the leaders into accepting the change. Accelerated cultural change by frequent communication, recognizing and rewarding the correct behavior, and creating north stars and champions. Implemented new agile processes and organization structure. Result is that the team has gone through the cultural transformation and mindset change. Doing more with less people. Accomplished Increased automation, cross functional teams, shift left, DevOps practices with reduced development cycle. KPIs about code, quality, agile and DevOps have been created, tracked and reported with focus on continuous improvement. The unit test coverage increased to 90%, new automation framework written and 10% of budget saved.
- I kicked off an architect community across the company. Result was that the architects started leveraging each other's knowledge and code, started doing biweekly tech talks, and started writing technical blogs

Publicis Sapient, India

Senior Director

Delivery Head, Digital Transformation Lead, Data Lead | 2016 to 2020

Delivery Head & Digital Transformation Leader For Tier 1 commodity client | 2019-2020 Transformation Consultant in Middle East | 2018-2019 Delivery Head, Digital & Data Transformation Lead For Tier I Investment bank in Europe | 2016-2018

Delivery Head, Agile Transformation Lead | 2013 to 2016

Delivery Head & Agile Transformation Lead For Tier I investment bank in US | 2014-2016 Product Delivery Head for Regulatory reporting product | 2013-2014

Operations, Hiring, Capacity Planning Lead | 2012-2013 ODC Delivery Head & Sales Lead | 2006-2011

Delivery Head, Digital Transformation Lead, Data Lead

- Built a Data Analytics & Insight Solutions to optimize pipelines for Tier I commodity client. I was the Delivery Head, Digital
 Transformation and Agile coach for the team. I used the strategy of training the team on agile and cloud prior to
 engagement. I created the agile and DevOps KPIs that were tracked. Ensured 100% unit and functional automation. Had
 all release pipelines automated. The result was that the team released to production every 2 weeks. 1M+ USD were saved
 in the first quarter
- For a Tier I investment bank built a Big Data lake for market risk data using Hadoop when no team was available. I created a strategy of slow ramp up, with experts up front, 100% automation, with 2 weekly releases, and bought the client into the strategy. I then trained a team of 60 Java developers in BigData with a 4 week hands on training, created multiple scrum teams with 1 SME per team and delivered a solution. Result was that the solution saved the bank a lot of money since they were able to decommission existing data stores.
- A Tier I bank Hadoop Data lake solution did not perform. Due to the immutable nature of HDFS a lot of rows were created resulting in slow queries. I led the research for the solution and found MongoDB to be faster and ported the read/write micro service to use MongoDB. The result was that the queries were very fast and we saved a 2M+ USD rewrite
- As Transformation consultant for Middle East I Identified speed, quality & value improvement opportunities using design thinking and value stream mapping for multiple bank teams. This resulted in business savings and increased productivity.

Delivery Head, Agile Transformation Lead

• Converted all the projects of a tier I investment bank ODC to agile. I laid out the agile transformation strategy for the ODC and brought in the client stakeholders. Then I implemented the strategy which included extensive training, agile coaching and agile intervention. Result was that within 1 year all the projects in the ODC were agile project with 50% of them doing more frequent deliveries.

ODC Delivery Head and Sales Lead

• I sold and grew an ODC for a Tier I investment bank. I built relationships with different client stakeholders, showcased the domain and technical expertise, negotiated the MSA with procurement, closed the deal and finally aggressively sold to different buying centers. The result was that I grew an ODC to 500+ people with 40M+ USD revenue

Fidelity Investments, USA

ODC Lead for Fidelity eBusiness Institutional, Bangalore | 2004-2006 Senior Development Manager, USA | 2002-2003 Development Manager, USA | 2001-2002 Architect & Lead Developer, USA | 2000-2001

- I needed to setup an ODC from scratch faced with no brand in Bangalore, and US staff unwilling to send any work
 offshore. I focused on hiring high quality talent, setup processes that ensured predictable high-quality delivery, and used
 my expert stakeholder management and people skills to ramp up the ODC to 100.
- As Senior Development Manager: Delivered the one Fidelity program that integrated retail and institutional sites for a uniform customer experience.

Infinium Software, USA Lead Developer | 1997-2000

NIIT Software Exports, India Developer | 1995-1997

Education

- Masters in Computer Science (Data Science) | University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign | Pursuing
- Bachelor in Technology (Computer Engineering) | Mangalore University

Keywords for Search Engine Optimization

Customer Success, Customer Focus, Continuous Improvement, Scaling team, Hiring, Strong communication, Interpersonal skills, Managing Enterprise Applications, Problem solving, Analytical, Strategic planning, Leading distributed team, Build high performance team, IT leader, Design, Development, Key Performance Indicators, Solution Integrator, Account management, Account Leader, Client Ilaison, Senior Vice President, Senior Director, Head of Engineering, Strategic thinking, Work under pressure, Attention to detail, Accountability, Payers of working experiences, Seasoned leader, Timely delivery, Large Scale, Knowledgeable, Innovative, Creative, Innovative, Innovative, Learner, Collaborative, Backend, Frontend, Infrastructure, Architecture, System Design, server-side engineering, UJ, Mentor, Subject matter expert, managing priorities, Scrumban, Kanban, Lean, Six Sigma, Business process re-engineering, Digital project, Robotic Process Automation RPA bots, cross-functional, Visual stream mapping VSM, Digital tools, CI CD, CI/CD, CI-CD, Influencing skills, people leadership, people management, impact, process improvement, domain exposure, planning, coordination, executive, senior leadership, strategic direction, best engineering practices, motivate, production, erecruitment, premier engineering institute, engineering excellence, Big Data, Full stack delivery, Enterprise & Scalable Architecture, Database, GTM (go to market) strategies, Technology And Business Leadership J Setting Up, Growing Teams | Digital Leader for Organizations, Building Products, Solutions, Applications - Consulting - Strategic Delivery Management - Senior Leadership Management - Strategy For Digital Transformation, Data Transformation, Data Science / Data Science / Data Engineering and Management - Strategic Project Management - Client & Stakeholder Management, Bris: Investment Banking | Capital Markets | Retail Banking | Investment Management, Equity, Equity Derivatives, Fixed Income, Market Risk, Credit Risk, Regulatory Reporting, Mortgages, Len

The leader in this role will provide technical oversight and direction to our software development team to ensure we deliver the best possible software solutions and ensure they are generating value through cost savings or incremental value. This leader will work closely with the user experience, product, IT, and process engineering teams to develop new products and prioritize deliver solutions across S&T core priorities.